<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bowers-isis-te-attribute-set-00" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ISIS TE Attribute Sets">
    Extensions to IS-IS to Associate TE Attributes with TE Attribute Sets
    </title>

    <author fullname="Chris Bowers" initials="C." surname="Bowers">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cbowers@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author initials="S." surname="Hegde" fullname="Shraddha Hegde">
		<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
		<address>
		<postal>
			<street>Embassy Business Park</street>
			<city>Bangalore</city>
			<region>KA</region>
			<code>560093</code>
			<country>India</country>
		</postal>
		<email>shraddha@juniper.net</email>
		</address>
	</author>

    <date day="2" month="July" year="2017"/>

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>ISIS Working Group</workgroup>

<abstract>

<t> Abstract text
</t>

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t> IS-IS encodings allow traffic engineering (TE) attributes, such as 
bandwidth, administrative groups, and SRLGs, to be associated with 
different links in the network topology. Different applications use 
these attributes to decide how traffic should be directed across the network.</t> 

<t> It can be useful for different applications to use different sets of attributes 
to decide how traffic is directed across the network.  Existing IS-IS encodings 
only allow for one set of TE attributes to be associated with a given link.  This
document specifies encodings that allow different sets of TE attributes to be 
associated with a given link.</t>

</section>

<section title="Basic assumptions">
<t> There are several different approaches that one could take to enable this.
The approach taken by this document is based on the following assumptions about
the use of this encoding.
</t>

<t>
<list style="hanging">

<t> The requirements of many current and future deployments of SR and 
RSVP are satisfied using the existing encodings that support a single 
set of TE attributes. The encodings described here allow the 
advertisement of multiple sets of TE attributes. They do so in a way 
that minimizes the burden, in terms of interoperability testing and 
software upgrades, on deployments that do not need this advanced 
fucntionality.</t> 

<t> Future applications are difficult to predict, especially as some 
network operators deploy their own customized, centralized controllers. 
The encodings described here does not try to associate TE attributes 
with particular applications. Instead, they allow TE attributes to be 
organized into sets, using groupings that make most sense for the 
network operator's particular use case. The network advertises these TE 
attributes with the associated TE attribute set identifiers, and 
different applications use this information as they see fit. The authors 
believe that this approach provides the greatest flexibility for those 
networks that are likely to need these advanced capabilities.</t> 

</list>
</t>


</section>
    

    
<section anchor="sec_te_attribute_set_id" title="TE Attribute Set Identifier">
   
<t> The new TE Attribute Set Identifier is a 32-bit value that identifies a 
set of attributes. All of the attributes advertised with a given value 
of the Attribute Set Identifier are considered to be part of the 
attribute set. This allows different applications to use different 
attribute sets, if desired. 
</t>

<t> The TE Attribute Set Identifier with a value of zero is special.  Existing 
encodings for advertising attributes that do not explicitly support the
inclusion of the TE Attribute Set Identifier are now understood to implicitly 
advertise attributes with the TE Attribute Set Identifier set to zero.
In this framework, existing implementations using the existing encodings 
already support the advertisement of attributes with the TE Attribute Set
Identifier = 0. 
</t>

<t> In order to ensure a consistent view of the attribute set scoped attributes,
for encodings that explicitly support the TE Attribute Set Identifier, 
advertising an attribute with TE Attribute Set Identifier set to 
zero is not allowed.
</t>

<t> From a standardization perspective, there is not intended to be any 
fixed mapping between a given TE Attribute Set Identifier and a given 
application. A network operator wishing to advertise different attribute 
sets could configure the network equipment to advertise attributes with 
different values of the TE Attribute Set Identifier based on their 
objectives. The different applications (be they controller-based 
applications or distributed applications) would make use of the 
different attribute sets based on convention within that network. 
</t>
      
</section>
    
<section anchor="sec_link_attribute_set_sub_tlv" title="Link Attribute Set sub-TLV">

<t> The Link Attribute Set sub-TLV is a new sub-TLV for TLVs 22, 23, 141, 
222, and 223. It allows different sets of link attributes to be 
advertised for the same link. This allows different applications to use 
different sets of attributes. 
</t>

<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Type:">To be assigned by IANA (suggested value 101)</t>

<t hangText="Length:">Number of octets in the value field (1 octet)</t>

<t hangText="Value:">

	<list style="hanging">
	
	<t hangText="TE Attribute Set Identifier:"> A 32-bit value containing the non-zero 
		TE Attribute Set Identifier that identifies a set of attributes. The Link 
		Attribute Set sub-TLV MUST be ignored if the TE Attribute Set Identifier is 
		zero. This ensures a consistent view of the attribute set scoped link 
		attributes, where the Link Attribute sub-TLVs advertised directly 
		in TLV#22 are now understood to be implicitly advertised with the
		TE Attribute Set Identifier equal to zero. </t>

	<t hangText="Link Attribute sub-sub-TLVs:"> The format of these Link Attribute 
		sub-sub-TLVs matches the existing formats for the Link Attribute 
		sub-TLVs defined in <xref target="RFC5305"/> and <xref target="RFC7810"/>.
		Each Link Attribute sub-sub-TLV advertised in a given Link Attribute Set sub-TLV is 
		associated with the TE Attribute Set Identifier in the Link Attribute Set 
		sub-TLV. </t>

	</list>

 </t>


</list>
</t>
      

 
</section>
    

<section anchor="sec_attribute_set_scoped_srlg_tlv" title="TE Attribute Set Scoped SRLG TLV">

<t> A new TLV is defined to allow SRLGs to be advertised for a given link 
and associated with a specific attribute set identifier. Although 
similar in functionality to TLV 138 (defined by <xref 
target="RFC5307"/>) and TLV 139 (defined by <xref target="RFC6119"/>), 
a single TLV provides support for IPv4, IPv6, and unnumbered identifiers 
for a link. Unlike TLVs 138/139 it utilizes sub-TLVs to encode the link 
identifiers in order to provide the flexible formatting required to 
support multiple link identifier types. 
</t>

<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Type:">To be assigned by IANA (suggested value 238)</t>

<t hangText="Length:">Number of octets in the value field (1 octet)</t>

<t hangText="Value:">

	<list style="hanging">
	
	<t hangText="Neighbor System-ID + pseudo-node ID (7 octets)"> </t>

	<t hangText="TE Attribute Set Identifier:"> A 32-bit value containing the non-zero 
		TE Attribute Set Identifier that identifies a set of attributes. The 
		TE Attribute Set Scoped SRLG TLV MUST be ignored if the TE Attribute Set Identifier is 
		zero. This ensures a consistent view of the attribute set scoped link 
		attributes, where the SRLGs advertised directly in TLV#138 and TLV#139
		are now understood to be implicitly advertised with the
		TE Attribute Set Identifier equal to zero.</t>

	<t hangText="Length of sub-TLVs in octets (1 octet)"> </t>
	<t hangText="Link Identifier sub-TLVs (variable)"> </t>
	<t hangText="0 or more SRLG Values (Each value is 4 octets)"> </t>

	</list>

 </t>
 
 <t>
The following Link Identifier sub-TLVs are defined. The type
values are suggested and will be assigned by IANA - but as
the formats are identical to existing sub-TLVs defined for
TLVs 22, 23, 141, 222, and 223 the use of the suggested sub-TLV
types is strongly encouraged.
</t>

</list>
</t>
     
<t>
At least one set of link identifiers (IPv4, IPv6, or unnumbered) MUST
be present.  TLVs which do not meet this requirement MUST be ignored.
</t>	 

<t>
Multiple TLVs for the same link MAY be advertised.
</t>
 
</section>
    
<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>IANA is requested to create a new sub-TLV, the Link Attribute 
Set sub-TLV for TLVs 22, 23, 141, 222, and 223.</t>
	  
<figure>
<artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Type     Description                 22 23 141 222 223 Ref.
-------  --------------------------- -- -- --- --- --- -------
TBA1     Link Attribute Set sub-TLV  y  y   y   y   y  [This
                                                        draft]
]]></artwork>
</figure> 

<t>IANA is requested to create a new TLV, the TE Attribute Set 
Scoped SRLG TLV.</t>
	  
<figure>
<artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Type     Description             IIH SNP LSP Purge Ref.
-------  ----------------------- --- --- --- ----- ------
TBA2     TE Attribute Set Scoped  n   n   y    n   [This
         SRLG TLV                                  draft]
]]></artwork>
</figure> 

</section>
    
    <section title="Management Considerations">
      <t>TBD
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t> TBD
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" toc="default">
	  <t> The basic format for the encoding of the Link Attribute Set sub-TLV and the 
		TE Attribute Set Scoped SRLG TLV follows the basic format of the encodings in 
		<xref target="I-D.ginsberg-isis-te-app"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
  
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5305.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5307.xml"?>
	  <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7810.xml"?>
    </references>
	
	 <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ginsberg-isis-te-app-00.xml"?>
    </references>
      
  </back>
</rfc>
